[Music]
last video I laid out the structure of a
neural network I'll give a quick recap
here just so that it's fresh in our
minds and then I have two main goals for
this video the first is to introduce the
idea of gradient descent which underlies
not only how neural networks learn but
how a lot of other machine learning
works as well then after that we're
going to dig in a little more to how
this particular Network performs and
what those hidden layers of neurons end
up actually looking
for as a reminder our goal here is the
classic example of handwritten digit
recognition the hello world of neural
networks these digits are rendered on a
28x 28 pixel grid each pixel with some
grayscale value between 0 and 1 those
are what determine the activations of
784 neurons in the input layer of the
network and then the activation for each
neuron in the following layers is based
on a weighted sum of all the activations
in the previous layer plus some special
number called a
bias then you compose that sum with some
other function like the sigmoid squish
ification or aayu the way that I walked
through last video in total given the
somewhat arbitrary choice of two hidden
layers here with 16 neurons each the
network has about 13,000 weights and
biases that we can adjust and it's these
values that determine what exactly the
network you know actually does then what
we mean when we say that this network
classifies a given digit is that the
brightest of those 10 neurons into the
final layer corresponds to that digit
and remember the motivation that we had
in mind here for the layered structure
was that maybe the second layer could
pick up on the edges and the third layer
might pick up on patterns like loops and
lines and the last one could just piece
together those patterns to recognize
digits so here we learn how the network
learns what we want is an algorithm
where you can show this network a whole
bunch of training data which comes in
the form of a bunch of different images
of handwritten digits along with labels
for what they're supposed to be and
it'll adjust those 13,000 weights and
biases so as to improve its performance
on the training data hopefully this
layered structure will mean that what it
learns generalizes to images beyond that
training data and the way we test that
is that after you train the network you
show it more labeled data that it's
never seen before and you see how
accurately it classifies those new
images
fortunately for us and what makes this
such a common example to start with is
that the good people behind the Mist
database have put together a collection
of tens of thousands of handwritten
digit images each one labeled with the
numbers that they're supposed to be and
as provocative as it is to describe a
machine as learning once you actually
see how it works it feels a lot less
like some crazy sci-fi premise and a lot
more like well a calculus exercise I
mean basically it comes down to finding
the minimum of a certain function
remember conceptually we're thinking of
each neuron as being connected to all of
the neurons in the previous layer and
the weights in the weighted sum defining
its activation are kind of like the
strengths of those connections and the
bias is some indication of whether that
neuron tends to be active or inactive
and to start things off we're just going
to initialize all of those weights and
biases totally randomly needless to say
this network is going to perform pretty
horribly on a given training example
since it's just doing something random
for example you feed in this image of a
three and the output layer it just looks
like a mess so what you do is you define
a cost function a way of telling the
computer no bad computer that output
should have activations which are zero
for most neurons but one for this neuron
what you gave me is utter trash to say
that a little more mathematically what
you do is add up the squares of the
differences between each of those trash
output activations and the value that
you want them to have and this is what
we'll call the cost of a single training
example notice this sum is small when
the network confidently classifies the
image
correctly but it's large when the
network seems like it doesn't really
know what it's
doing so then what you do is consider
the average cost over all of the tens of
thousands of training examples at your
disposal this average cost is our
measure for how how lousy the network is
and how bad the computer should feel and
that's a complicated thing remember how
the network itself was basically a
function one that takes in 784 numbers
as inputs the pixel values and spits out
10 numbers as its output and in a since
it's parameterized by all these weights
and biases well the cost function is a
layer of complexity on top of that it
takes as its input those 13,000 or so
weights and biases and it spits out a
single number describing how bad those
weights and biases are and the way it's
defined depends on the Network's
Behavior over all the tens of thousands
of pieces of training data that's a lot
to think
about but just telling the computer what
a crappy job it's doing isn't very
helpful you want to tell it how to
change those weights and biases so that
it gets better to make it easier rather
than struggling to imagine a function
with 13,000 inputs just imagine a simple
function that has one number as an input
and one number as an output how do you
find an input that minimizes the value
of this function calculus students will
know that you can sometimes figure out
that minimum explicitly but that's not
always feasible for really complicated
functions certainly not in the 13,000
input version of this situation for our
crazy complicated neural network cost
function a more flexible tactic is to
start at any all input and figure out
which direction you should step to make
that output lower specifically if you
can figure out the slope of the function
where you are then shift to the left if
that slope is positive and shift the
input to the right if that slope is
negative if you do this repeatedly at
each point checking the new slope and
taking the appropriate step you're going
to approach some local minimum of the
function and the image you might have in
mind here is a ball rolling down a hill
and notice even for this really
simplified single input function there
are many possible valleys that you might
land in depending on which random input
you start at and there's no guarantee
that the local minimum you land in is
going to be the smallest possible value
of the cost function that's going to
carry over to our neural network case as
well and I also want you to notice how
if you make your step sizes proportional
to the slope then when the slope is
flattening out towards the minimum your
steps get smaller and smaller and that
kind of helps you from
overshooting bumping up the complexity a
bit imagine instead a function with two
inputs and one output you might think of
the input space as the XY plane and the
cost function as being graphed as a
surface above it now instead of asking
about the slope of the function you have
to ask which direction should you step
in this input space so is to decrease
the output of the function most quickly
in other words what's the downhill
Direction and again it's helpful to
think of a ball rolling down that Hill
those of you familiar with multivariable
Calculus will know know that the
gradient of a function gives you the
direction of steepest Ascent basically
which direction should you step to
increase the function most quickly
naturally enough taking the negative of
that gradient gives you the direction to
step that decreases the function most
quickly and even more than that the
length of this gradient Vector is
actually an indication for just how
steep that steepest slope is now if
you're unfamiliar with multivariable
Calculus and you want to learn more
check out some of the work that I did
for k on the topic Honestly though all
that matters for you and me right now is
that in principle there exists a way to
compute this Vector this Vector that
tells you what the downhill direction is
and how steep it is you'll be okay if
that's all you know and you're not rock
solid on the
details cuz if you can get that the
algorithm for minimizing the function is
to compute this gradient Direction then
take a small step downhill and just
repeat that over and
over it's the same basic idea for
function that has 13,000 inputs instead
of two inputs imagine organizing all
13,000 weights and biases of our Network
into a giant column Vector the negative
gradient of the cost function is just a
vector it's some direction inside this
insanely huge input space that tells you
which nudges to all of those numbers is
going to cause the most rapid decrease
to the cost function and of course with
our specially designed cost function
changing the weights of and biases to
decrease it means making the output of
the network on each piece of training
data look less like a random array of 10
values and more like an actual decision
that we want it to make it's important
to remember this cost function involves
an average over all of the training data
so if you minimize it it means it's a
better performance on all of those
samples the algorithm for computing this
gradient efficiently which is
effectively the heart of how a neural
network learns is called back
propagation and it's what I'm going to
be talking about next video there I
really want to take the time to walk
through what exactly happens to each
weight and each bias for a given piece
of training data trying to give an
intuitive feel for what's happening
beyond the pile of relevant calculus and
formulas Right Here Right Now the main
thing I want you to know independent of
implementation details is that what we
mean when we talk about a network
learning is that it's just minimizing a
cost function and notice one consequence
of that is that it's important for this
cost function to have a nice smooth
output so that we can find a local
minimum by taking little steps
downhill this is why by the way
artificial neurons have continuously
ranging activations rather than simply
being active or inactive in a binary way
the way that biological neurons
are this process of repeatedly nudging
an input of a function by some multiple
of the negative gradient is called
gradient descent it's a way to converge
towards some local minimum of a cost
function basically a valley in this
graph I'm still showing the picture of a
function with two inputs of course
because nudges in a 13,000 dimensional
inut space are a little hard to wrap
your mind around but there is actually a
nice non-spatial way to think about this
each component of the negative gradient
tells us two things the sign of course
tells us whether the corresponding
component of the input Vector should be
nudged up or down but importantly the
relative magnitudes of all these
components
kind of tells you which changes matter
more you see in our Network an
adjustment to one of the weights might
have a much greater impact on the cost
function than the adjustment to some
other
weight some of these connections just
matter more for our training data so a
way that you can think about this
gradient Vector of our mind-warping
massive cost function is that it encodes
the relative importance of each weight
and bias that is which of these changes
is going to carry the most bang for your
buck this really is just another way of
thinking about direction to take a
simpler example if you have some
function with two variables as an input
and you compute that its gradient at
some particular Point comes out as
31 then on the one hand you can
interpret that as saying that when
you're standing at that input moving
along this direction increases the
function most quickly that when you
graph the function above the plane of
input points that Vector is what's
giving you the straight uphill Direction
but another way to read that is to say
that changes to this first variable have
three times the importance as changes to
the second variable that at least in the
neighborhood of the relevant input
nudging the x value carries a lot more
bang for your
buck all right let's zoom out and sum up
where we are so far the network itself
is this function with 784 inputs and 10
outputs defined in terms of all of these
weighted sums the cost function is a
layer of complexity on top of that it
takes the 13,000 weights and biases as
inputs and spits out a single measure of
lousiness based on the training examples
and the gradient of the cost function is
one more layer of complexity still it
tells us what nudges to all of these
weights and biases cause the fastest
change to the value of the cost function
which you might interpret as saying
which changes to which weights matter
the most
so when you initialize the network with
random weights and biases and adjust
them many times based on this gradient
descent process how well does it
actually perform on images that it's
never seen before well the one that I've
described here with the two hidden
layers of 16 neurons each chosen mostly
for aesthetic reasons well it's not bad
it classifies about 96% of the new
images that it sees correctly and
honestly if you look at some of the
examples that it messes up on you kind
of feel compelled to cut it a little
slack now if you play around with the
hidden layer structure and make a couple
tweaks you can get this up to 98% and
that's pretty good it's not the best you
can certainly get better performance by
getting more sophisticated than this
plain vanilla network but given how
daunting the initial task is I just
think there's something incredible about
any network doing this well on images
that it's never seen before given that
we never specifically told it what
patterns to look
for originally the way that I motivated
this structure was by describing a hope
that we might have that the second layer
might pick up on little edges that the
third layer would piece together those
edges to recognize loops and longer
lines and that those might be pieced
together to recognize digits so is this
what our network is actually doing well
for this one at least not at all
remember how last video we looked at how
the weights of the connections from all
of the neurons in the first layer to a
given neuron in the second layer can be
visualized as a given pixel pattern that
that second layer neuron is picking up
on well when we actually do that for the
weights associated with these
transitions from the first layer to the
next instead of picking up on isolated
little edges here and there they look
well almost random just with some very
loose patterns in the middle there it
would seem that in the unfathomably
large 13,000 dimensional space of
possible weights and and biases our
Network found itself a happy little
local minimum that despite successfully
classifying most images doesn't exactly
pick up on the patterns that we might
have hoped for and to really drive this
point home watch what happens when you
input a random image if the system was
smart you might expect it to either feel
uncertain maybe not really activating
any of those 10 output neurons or
activating them all evenly but instead
it confidently gives you some nonsense
answer as if it feels as sure that this
random noise as a five as it does that
an actual image of a five is a five
phrased differently even if this network
can recognize digits pretty well it has
no idea how to draw them a lot of this
is because it's such a tightly
constrained training setup I mean put
yourself in the Network's shoes here
from its point of view the entire
universe consists of nothing but clearly
defined unmoving digits centered in a
tiny grid and its cost function just
never gave it any incentive to be
anything but utterly confident in its
decisions so with this as the image of
what those second layer neurons are
really doing you might wonder why I
would introduce this network with the
motivation of picking up on edges and
patterns I mean that's just not at all
what it ends up doing well this is not
meant to be our end goal but instead a
starting point frankly this is old
technology the kind researched in the '
80s and '90s and you do need to
understand it before you can understand
more detailed modern variants and it
clearly is capable of solving some
interesting problems s but the more you
dig into what those hidden layers are
really doing the less intelligent it
seems Shifting the focus for a moment
from how networks learn to how you learn
that'll only happen if you engage
actively with the material here somehow
one pretty simple thing that I want you
to do is just pause right now and think
deeply for a moment about what changes
you might make to this system and how it
perceives images if you wanted it to
better pick up on things like edges and
patterns but better than that to
actually engage with the material I
highly recommend the book by Michael
neelen on deep learning and neural
networks in it you can find the code and
the data to download and play with for
this exact example and the book will
walk you through step by step what that
code is doing what's awesome is that
this book is free and publicly available
so if you do get something out of it
consider joining me in making a donation
towards neel's efforts I've also linked
a couple other resources that I like a
lot in the description including the
phenomenal and beautiful blog post by
Chris Ola and the articles in
distill to close things off here for the
last few minutes I want to jump back
into a snippet of the interview that I
had with Lea Lee you might remember her
from the last video she did her PhD work
in deep learning and in this little
snippet she talks about two recent
papers that really dig into to how some
of the more modern image recognition
networks are actually learning just to
set up where we were in the conversation
the first paper took one of these
particularly deep neural networks that's
really good at image recognition and
instead of training it on a properly
labeled data set it shuffled all of the
labels around before training obviously
the testing accuracy here was going to
be no better than random since
everything's just randomly labeled but
it was still able to achieve the same
training accuracy as you would on a
properly labeled data set basically the
millions of weights for this particular
Network were enough for it to just
memorize the random data which kind of
Reon is the question for whether
minimizing this cost function actually
corresponds to any sort of structure in
the image or is it just you know
memorization the entire data set of what
the correct classification is and so a
couple of you know half a year later at
icml this year um there was not exactly
rebuttal paper paper that addressed some
aspects of like hey actually these
networks are doing something a little
bit smarter than that if you look at
that accuracy curve if you were just
training on a random data set that curve
sort of went down very you know very
slowly in almost kind of a linear
fashion so you're really struggling to
find that local Minima of possible you
know the right weights that would get
you that accuracy whereas if you're
actually training on a structured data
set one that has the right labels you
know you fiddle around a little bit in
the beginning but then you kind of
dropped very fast to get to that uh
accuracy level and so in some sense it
was easier to find that local Maxima and
so so was also interesting about that is
it it brings into light another paper
from actually a couple of years ago
which has a lot more uh simplifications
about the network layers but one of the
results was saying how if you look at
the optimization landscape the local
Minima that these networks tend to learn
are actually of equal quality so in some
sense if your data set is structured you
should be able to find that much more
easily my thanks as always to those of
you supporting on patreon I've said
before just what a game changer patreon
is but these videos really would not be
possible without you I also want to give
a special thanks to the VC firm amplify
Partners in their support of these
initial videos in the series
[Music]